### Ramprasaath R. Selvaraju

scholar.google www.ramselvaraju.com

**☑** ramprasaath.21@gmail.com **J** (+1) 434-616-0082

**SUMMARY** 

PROFESSIONAL Research Scientist with 5 years of industry experience working on topics related to Explainable-AI, Foundation Models and Robustness. Previously Senior Research Scientist at Salesforce Research and Ph.D from Georgia Tech.

RESEARCH **INTERESTS**  Computer Vision, Explainable-AI, LLMs, Vision and Language

**EMPLOYMENT** 

Apple, Sunnyvale

2023 - now

Senior Research Scientist

Machine Learning for Apple Vision Pro

Artera AI, Los Altos

2022 - 2023

Senior Machine Learning Scientist

Precision Medicine through Computer Vision

Salesforce Research, Palo Alto

2020 - 2022

Senior Research Scientist

Open ended research at the intersection of Explainable-AI, Robustness, and Large Scale Vision and Language Pretraining

**EDUCATION** 

### Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta

Ph.D in Computer Science

Dissertation Title: Explaining Model Decisions and Correcting them via Human Feedback

Birla Institute of Technology & Science (BITS)-Pilani Bachelor of Engineering (Honor) in Electrical and Electronics

Master of Science (Honor) in Physics

AWARDS

Recognized among the Top-100 scholars in the AMinor 2022 AI 2000 Most influential scholars in Computer Vision between 2012-2021.

**INTERNSHIPS** 

#### Microsoft Research, Seattle

Summer 2019

With Ece Kamar, Besmira Nushi and Eric Horvitz

Towards evaluating and encouraging human-like reasoning abilities in deep models.

Tesla Autopilot, Palo Alto

Spring 2019

With Andrej Karpathy

Preventing failures of autonomous systems in case of rarely occurring scenarios.

Samsung Research America, Mountain View

Summer 2018

With Yilin Shen and Hongxia Jia

Developing algorithms for grounding and unbiasing deep vision and language models.

Facebook, Menlo Park

Spring 2017

With Peter Vajda and Devi Parikh

Developing a framework for interpreting and visualizing Facebook's deep models.

### Virginia Tech, Blacksburg

Spring 2015

With Devi Parikh

Building curious systems that ask natural language questions about an image.

### Oxford University, Oxford

Fall 2014

With Philip H.S Torr and Stephen Hicks

Developing interactive augmented reality system for visually impaired users.

### Brown University, Providence

Summer 2013

With Benjamin Kimia

Designing a vision-based navigation system to help visually impaired people navigate indoor environments.

#### **PATENTS**

Systems and methods for contrastive pretraining with video tracking supervision

B. Chen, R.R. Selvaraju and N. Naik

US Patent App. 12/106,541.

## Systems and methods for contrastive attention-supervised tuning R.R. Selvaraju and N. Naik

 $\overline{\text{US Patent App.}}\ 17/209,011\ \text{and}\ 17/209,013.$ 

## JOURNAL ARTICLES

## Grad-CAM: Visual Explanations from Deep Networks via Gradient-based Localization

**R.R. Selvaraju**, M. Cogswell, A. Das, R. Vedantam, D. Parikh, and D. Batra *International Journal of Computer Vision (IJCV)*, 2019.

# Reframing Explanation as an Interactive Medium: The EQUAS (Explainable QUestion Answering System) Project

D. Batra, W. Ferguson, R. Mooney, D. Parikh, A. Torralba, D. Bau, D. Diller, J. Fasching, J. Kaufman, Y. Goyal, J. Miller, K. Moffitt, A. Oca, <u>R.R. Selvaraju</u>, A. Shrivastava, J. Wu

Applied AI Letters, 2021.

## CONFERENCE PAPERS

### Development and validation of an AI-derived digital pathology-based biomarker

Andrew Armstrong, Vinnie Liu, **R.R. Selvaraju**, Emmalyn Chen, et al. American Society of Clinical Oncology (ASCO), 2023.

## CLIP-Lite: Information Efficient Visual Representation Learning from Textual Annotations

A. Srivastava, **R.R. Selvaraju**, N. Naik, V. Ordonez *AISTATS*, 2023.

# PreViTS: Contrastive Pretraining with Video Tracking Supervision B. Chen, R.R. Selvaraju, S. Chang, J. Niebles, N. Naik WACV, 2023.

## TAG: Boosting Text-VQA via Text-aware Visual Question-answer Generation

J. Wang, M. Gao, Y. Hu, <u>R.R. Selvaraju</u>, C. Ramaiah, R. Xu, J. Jaja, L. Davis  $BMVC,\,2022.$ 

## Align before Fuse: Vision and Language Representation Learning with Momentum Distillation

J. Li, R.R. Selvaraju, A. Gotmare, S. Joty, C. Xiong, S. Hoi Neurl PS, 2021.

## SOrT-ing VQA Models: Contrastive Gradient Learning for Improved Consistency

S. Dharur, P. Tendulkar, D. Batra, D. Parikh, R.R. Selvaraju NAACL, 2021.

## CASTing Your Model: Learning to Localize Improves Self-Supervised Representations

R.R. Selvaraju\*, K. Desai\*, J. Johnson, N. Naik CVPR, 2021.

SQuINTing at VQA Models: Interrogating VQA Models with Sub-Questions R.R. Selvaraju, P. Tendulkar, D. Parikh, E. Horvitz, M. Ribeiro, B. Nushi, E. Kamar  $\overline{CVPR}$ , 2020.

## Taking a HINT: Leveraging Explanations to Make Vision & Language Models More Grounded

R.R. Selvaraju, S. Lee, Y. Shen, H. Jia, S. Ghosh, L. Heck, D. Batra, D. Parikh *ICCV*, 2019.

# Trick or TReAT: Thematic Reinforcement for Artistic Typography P. Tendulkar, K. Krishna, R.R. Selvaraju, D. Parikh *ICCC*, 2019.

## Choose Your Neuron: Incorporating Domain Knowledge into Deep Networks via Neuron Importance

R.R. Selvaraju\*, P. Chattopadhyay\*, M. Elhoseini, T. Sharma, D. Batra, D. Parikh, S. Lee *ECCV*, 2018.

## Diverse Beam Search: Decoding Diverse Solutions from Neural Sequence Models

A. Vijayakumar, M. Cogswell, <u>R.R. Selvaraju</u>, Q. Sun, S. Lee, D. Crandall, D. Batra AAAI, 2018.

## Grad-CAM: Visual Explanations from Deep Networks via Gradient-based Localization

**R.R. Selvaraju**, M. Cogswell, A. Das, R. Vedantam, D. Parikh, D. Batra *ICCV*, 2017.

### Counting Everyday Objects in Everyday Scenes

P. Chattopadhyay, R. Vedantam, **R.R. Selvaraju**, D. Batra, D. Parikh *CVPR*, 2017.

## The Semantic Paintbrush: Interactive 3D Mapping and Recognition in Large Outdoor Spaces

M. Ondrej, V. Vineet, M. Lidegaard, R.R. Selvaraju, M. Niener, S. Golodetz, S.

Hicks, P. Prez, S. Izadi, P. Torr *CHI*, 2015.

# Automated Colorimetric Analysis in Paper-based Sensors S. Garg, R.R. Selvaraju, S. Kapur, K. Rao *ICIP*, 2014.

### WORKSHOP PAPERS

Can domain adaptation make object recognition work for everyone? V. Prabhu, R.R. Selvaraju, J. Hoffman, N. Naik

CVPR'22 Workshop on Learning with Limited Labelled Data.

# ${\bf SOr T\text{-}ing\ VQA\ Models:\ Contrastive\ Gradient\ Learning\ for\ Improved\ Consistency}$

S. Dharur, P. Tendulkar, D. Batra, D. Parikh, R.R. Selvaraju NeurIPS'20 Workshop on Interpretable Inductive Biases.

## Taking a HINT: Leveraging Explanations to Make Vision & Language Models More Grounded

R.R. Selvaraju, S. Lee, Y. Shen, H. Jia, S. Ghosh, D. Batra, D. Parikh ICLR'19 Workshop on Debug ML.

## Choose Your Neuron: Incorporating Domain Knowledge into Deep Networks via Neuron Importance

**R.R. Selvaraju**\*, P. Chattopadhyay\*, M. Elhoseini, T. Sharma, D. Batra, D. Parikh, S. Lee

NeurIPS'18 Workshop on Continual Learning, NeurIPS'18 VIGIL Workshop.

### Grad-CAM: Why did you say that?

R.R. Selvaraju, M. Cogswell, A. Das, R. Vedantam, D. Parikh, D. Batra NeurIPS'16 Workshop on Interpretable ML, CVPR'17 Workshop on Explainable CV.

### INVITED TALKS Explaining Model Decisions and Fixing them via Human Feedback

Stanford Medical AI Seminar, Fall 22

## Explaining Model Decisions and Correcting them through Focused Feedback

Towards Robust, Trustworthy, and Explainable Computer Vision (ICCV'21 Tutorial)

### Visualizing and Understanding CNNs

Deep Learning Lecture at Georgia Tech (Fall 19, 20, 21)

#### Towards Interpretable, Transparent and Unbiased AI

Microsoft AI Breakthroughs, Fall 18

### TEACHING Data Structures and Algorithms

Fall 15 - Spring 16

Teaching Assistant

### Towards Robust, Transparent and Explainable Computer Vision (ICCV'21) Tutorial Organizer

TECHNICAL

Languages: Python, MATLAB, C++, HTML

SKILLS Deep Learning Frameworks: PyTorch, Tensorflow, Caffe, Torch

SIDE PROJECTS Interpreting decisions from Deep RL agents trained for navigation Weak supervision and Generative models for semantic segmentation

Spring 2018 Exploring Curriculum Learning for deep models Spring 2015

RELEVANT COURSES

• Math Foundations of ML

• Adv. Computer Vision

• Adv. Machine Learning

• Deep Learning • Optim. in High-dim • Bayesian Statistics

• Prob. and Statistics

• Human Robot Interaction

Fall 2020

• Linear Algebra

REVIEWING

IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence (PAMI) 2018

British Machine Vision Conference (BMVC) 2022

Computer Vision and Image Understanding (CVIU) Journal 2019 Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR) 2017 - 2022 Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS) 2016, 2017 European Conference on Computer Vision (ECCV) 2018, 2020

IEEE International Conference on Computer Vision (ICCV) 2017, 2019, 2021

International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA) 2021

**EXTRA** CURRICULAR First Place, Divisionals and Second, Mid-Atlantic Table-Tennis Championship 2016 Represented Virginia Tech, US-Canada National Table-Tennis Championship 2016

REFERENCES

Dr. Devi Parikh, Associate Professor, Georgia Tech deviparikh.dp@gmail.com

Dr. Dhruv Batra, Associate Professor, Georgia Tech batradhruv@gmail.com

Dr. Nikhil Naik, Lead Research Scientist, Salesforce Research nnaik@salesforce.com

Dr. Ece Kamar, Managing Director @ AI Frontiers Lab, Microsoft Research

mar@microsoft.com

Dr. Stefan Lee, Assistant Professor, Oregon State University leestef@oregonstate.edu

Dr. Mohamed Elhoseiny, Assistant Professor, KAUST

hamed.elhoseiny@kaust.edu.sa